MOHAMMED HASHI MUSE

Contact Address: Address: Near Maansoor Hotel, Jigjigayar, koodbur District, Hargeisa, E-mail: meecaad18@gmail.com, Telephone: +252-63-4414693

PERSONAL DATA:

First Name: Mohammed Hashi Muse

Physical Street Address: Near maansoor, Hotel, jigjigayar, koodbuur district, Hargiesa, Somaliland

Telephone Mobile:+252-634414693/+252-65-9849001

Email: meecaad18@gmail.com

Marital Status: Single

Date of Birth: 11 November/1984

summary

Professional in Governance, Management, Education and IT sectors with vast knowledge in Management, Capacity building, Administration & Information Management Technology needs, with over 7 years of extensive experience in both Government and non-government organization. Having experience in the fields of administration, Management, Education, IT, financial procedures, organizational Management and Projects Management, I have Administration experience for the projects including the Rule of Law programme, Child protection and also having experience in the fields of Capacity building and developing strategies, policies, software application and database management within different institutions in both government and non-government institutions. Specializing in programme management, institutional development and change management. I have participated in management complex project within different institutions and three years teaching experience at the higher education, universities levels with students diverse in ability, and ethnicity. Areas of teaching competence include an introduction to the computer, Database Management System, MIS and Statistics Political for Social Science. Experienced in developing course curricula as well as executing field trips, computer laboratory exercises, and other activities beyond computer lectures

EDUCATION:

- Master of Business Administration (MBA), Sikkim Manipal University of Health, Medical and Technological Sciences, India, 2008 to 2010
- ➤ BSC, Osmania University, Hyderabad, India, 08/2004 to 07/2007.
- > Diploma in HR, The all India Institute of Arts Management and computer Studies,
- > Diploma in Database Management system (oracle 10g), PEERS INSTITUTE2009
- > Diploma in Ms-Access, Gemestect 2008
- > Second Leaving Certificate Time-Adde Secondary School, 1999 2003
- ➤ Elementary and intermediate school 1991-1999

Achievements

- ✓ Analyzed local value chain and market system for enhancing resilience in Somaliland communities
- ✓ addressed the market constraints for enhancing resilience in Somaliland communities
- analyzed and described market constraints as they relate to the target group
- ✓ Identified the areas in the value chain where older men and women and persons with disability can be engaged
- ✓ prepared and submitted the final report

- ✓ Participated preparation of National investment policy
- ✓ prepared 2019 Annual work plan of MOIP and first of draft of MOIP's five years strategy
- ✓ prepared industrial park, capacity building and special economic zone concept notes
- ✓ Prepared and finalized National Lawyer's Licensing & Ethics Committee one year strategy plan
- ✓ Collected all the licensed lawyer's documents and review and registered 100 licensed lawyers
- ✓ Prepared and finalized Somaliland Lawyer's Five years Strategy plan
- ✓ Prepared SOLLA Manual guidelines including: SOLLA External Relation Manual, communication procedure manual, Financial Manual, Management practice manual and Governance Manual.
- ✓ Participated preparation for Eragove and Las'anod district development Plan 2016-2016 consultation with local council and community
- ✓ Participated Gabiley Review Regional Development plan 2012-2014
- ✓ Developed Gabiley Regional Development plan 2016-2017
- ✓ Participated Civil registry manual guideline for local government
- ✓ Participated preparation of the Somaliland National Development Plan I and II
- ✓ Developed National Civil Registration Policy
- ✓ Prepared procedures and Manual Guideline of Birth and Death registration training manual for local governments
- ✓ Participated Functional review (restructuring and their roles and responsibilities)
- ✓ Participated National identity policy development
- ✓ Developed Civil registration management system for Hargiesa District as Pilot
- ✓ Prepared first draft of IT training manual for secondary teacher upgrading certificate
- ✓ Participated Strategic Development Plan For the Land and Urban Management Institute

WORK HISTORY:

1. Head of Trainings of HRM department of Ministry of Investment Promotion and Industrial

- > recommends, designs, and implements innovative learning and development programs throughout the entire employment lifecycle, including onboarding, career development, wellness, and leadership growth.
- Continually monitors and evaluates effectiveness of programs and makes needed adjustments.
 Monitor program effectiveness, track outcomes, and make adjustments as needed.
- developing reports, offering training on online tools, and staying updated on educational trends to improve efficiency and effectiveness within the organization

2. Head of ICT, Somaliland National AIDS Commission (SONAC) (Jan 2020 - Dec-2023)

- Leads the ICT strategy, system development, and technical management.
- > Ensures database integrity, security, and performance.
- Oversees system compliance with internal and external standards.
- Provides training, support, and advice to staff and management.
- Manages ICT resource acquisition, system security, and project planning
- **3.** Director of Communication and Public Relations, Ministry of Investment Promotion (Dec 2018 Jan 2020):
 - Managed communication strategies and media relations.
 - Prepared and disseminated public materials and reports.

- Coordinated press conferences and public relations activities.
- Prepared risk management and progress reports

4. Executive Director, Somaliland Lawyer's Association (SOLLA), Hargeisa, September 2018 August 2020,

- Strategic Planning. Implement the goals of the Association as developed and approved by the Board.
- Policy and Program. Recommend and implement Board approved policies and programs.
- **Procedure**. Develop and implement Association operating procedures.
- **Public Representative**. Serve as the public representative of the Association and promote the Association and its members in and to the public.
- Office Administration. Manage Association staff and business to ensure smooth operation of the office and the Association.
- Staff Management. Records Management, Recruitment & Selection, supervise, evaluate, and terminate Association staff. Define and delegate staff duties. Motivate and inspire staff to provide excellent service to its members and the public.
- **Finance**. Manage the financial affairs of the Association by providing regular financial reports to the Board of Governors, securing clean annual audits, and reporting annually to the membership on the budget and financial condition of the Association.
- Budget. Prepare an annual, balanced budget for review and adoption by the Board.
- **Information Technology**. Ensure the Association stays current with technical improvements in order to provide appropriate and current information and services to the membership.
- Liaison. Serve as the Association liaison to government and private organizations at local, and national levels in order to enhance the image of the Association and make use of the resources of those organizations.
- Board. Provide staff support to the Board of Governors by setting agendas, scheduling meetings, and providing advice and counsel on governance issues, policies, procedures, and other matters under consideration.
- **Annual Meeting**. Oversee all aspects of the annual meeting planning to ensure a successful event that provides educational and social opportunities for the membership.
- Committee, Commission, Section and Task Force Responsibilities. Coordinate and staff meetings
 for numerous committees, commissions, sections, and task forces as needed or as required by statute
 or rule.
- Other Duties: Other duties may be assigned by the Board of Governors, as needed.

5. Admin & Finance Director, National Lawyer's Licensing & Ethics Committee(NLLEC), September-Dec 2018

- ✓ Establishment of the office: preparing the office of the committee and the structure
- ✓ preparing short time work plan of the office
- ✓ reviewing the existing By-Law, Regulations, policies, procedures and manual guidelines
- ✓ **Office Administration**. Managing staff and business to ensure smooth operation of the office, including Records Management, preparing Recruitment & Selection procedures, supervise, evaluate, and terminate Committee staff. Define and delegate staff duties. Motivate and inspire staff to provide excellent service to its members and the public.
- ✓ **Finance**. Manage the financial affairs of the Committee by providing regular financial reports to the Committee, securing clean annual audits, and reporting annually to the membership on the budget and financial condition of the Association.
- ✓ Budget. Prepare an annual, balanced budget for review and adoption by the Committee.
- ✓ **Information Technology**. Ensure the Committee stays current with technical improvements in order to provide appropriate and current information and services to the membership.

- ✓ Liaison. Serve as the Association liaison to government and private organizations at local, and national levels in order to enhance the image of the Association and make use of the resources of those organizations.
- ✓ Committee. Provide staff support to the Committee by setting agendas, scheduling meetings, and providing advice and counsel on governance issues, policies, procedures, and other matters under consideration.
- ✓ Other Duties: Other duties may be assigned by the Committee, as needed.

6. Program Coordinator in Minister of state of the Peace Building & Development of the Eastern Regions from May 2016 to 2016 December

- coordinating and organizing the relation between the state minister office and international organization and other governmental institutions
- developing a comprehensive plan of eastern regions and districts
- participating Somaliland National Development plan 2
- preparing conflict resolution concept note for eastern regions of Somaliland
- preparing Ceergaabo and Lascaanood Districts Development Plan for 2016-2017
- 7. Public Administration Specialist in Ministry of Interior/UNICEF

Feb 2015 to Mar 2016

- 8. IOM/CTG Consultant Public Administration Specialist (Identity), Ministry of Interior (MOI) Jun 14 to Jan 15
- 9. Database Administrator in MINISTRY OF INTERIOR

Jun 2013 to Jun 2014

10. Lecturer at UNIVERSITY OF HARGEISA (UOH)

From Jan 2011 -June, 2013

Preparing and deliver lectures to the students on topics such as Relational Database Management System(RDBM), introduction to computer and Statistical Package for Social science(SPSS), Evaluate and grade students' class work, laboratory work, assignments, and papers, Preparing course materials such as syllabi, homework assignments, and handouts. Planning, evaluating, and revising curricula, course content, and course materials and methods of instruction, Initiate, facilitate, and moderate classroom discussions and Maintain student attendance records, grades, and other required records. Keep abreast of developments in the field by reading current literature, talking with colleagues, and participating in professional conferences and as well as Maintain regularly scheduled office hours to advise and assist students. Supervise students' laboratory work.

lecturer for the computer introduction at Faculty of Economic and Political science

• Teaching load includes participation in introduction to computer, creating document, saving document, modifying document, creating spreadsheet, function mathematical in excel, entering data, analyzing data, saving, creating presentation and database.

lecturer for the Statistical Package for Social science at Faculty of Economic and Political science Lecturer for the Statistical Package for Social science at Faculty of Economic and Political science in the role of

- preparing Course Materials including syllabi, deliver lecture notes, laboratory work, assignments, and papers and software CD's, Maintain regularly scheduled office hours to advise and assist students. Supervise students' laboratory work and
- Teaching load includes participation in statistical Package for Social science, installing process, preparing data, data management, creating, Entering and Cleaning Data, Data analysis

lecturer for Relational Database Management System (RDMS)

lecturer Database Administration course for the final year student in the faculty of information technology in the role of

 Teaching Relational Database Management System (RDMS) including Creating New databases, Inserting and Updating the database forms, Different between Databases such as (MySQL, SQL, MSSQL, Sybase Databases) and how to create online databases which can be accessed WAN network and etc.

Lecturer for database administrator (oracle 10g) at Alpha university July 2011-Nov 2012

lecturer Database Administration (Oracle 10g) course for the final year student in the faculty of information technology

Lecturer for Management Information System (MIS) at Time-Ade university July 2012-July 2013 Lecturer for system analysis and data management at Fairland university from July 2011-Nov 2012

11. ADMIN AND FINANCE ASISTANT IN KABA MICROFINANCE ORGANIZATION 2011

12. Data Entry at Cash instant (Dahabshiil)

2008-2009

13. Agri private Project Private Limited New Delhi, India

2009-2010

SHORT TIME WORKS

Drafting policy and website designer at Smartcode Law Firm

Worked as short time consulting for reviewing HR policy of Save the Children, drafting Smartcode law firm policy and designing Smartcode law firm website "www.smartcodelf.com"

Drafting land strategy, Minister of Public Work and Housing from Jan 2013 to Jun 2013

Worked as 6 month short time contract consulting for drafting and developing land Strategy plan.

Policy drafting, Ministry of technology, research and coordination of two houses from Oct 2014 to Nov 2014

Worked as 3 months Short time Consultant for drafting information technology policy and establishment of organizational structure and its department with drafting terms of references

Reporting writer at Ministry of Agriculture

Worked as Monitoring and Evaluation mission report for one month

ToT lecturer, Ministry of Education and Science

worked as lecturer for the 2 months training of teachers program for the secondary schools teachers, implementing by the ministry of education and sciences and supporting by the MerCrop and Save the Children in the hosting of Mucaarif Secondary school compus.

Drafting Regional Development plan for the Gabiley and Maroodi-Jeex Regions

worked as short time consultant for the drafting of Regional Development plan(GRDP1 & MJRDPI)

HIV/AIDs Commission for Drafting HR Manual Guideline

software Developer at Alpha university

Working as short time software developer for developing student management system using php program and mysql database, which "Alpha Student Management System"

SKILLS

Microsoft Office, Database management system, Application developer, IT Operations, IT Solutions,

Capacity Building, Word, Excel, Access & PowerPoint, Quick books, Tally, Peachtree, AIMS, & PIMS, Time Management, Event Planning, Microsoft Excel, IT Security, Policies, IT Service, Management, IT Strategy, Research, Teamwork, Photoshop, Social Media, C/C++, Java, HTML, Operating system

Other Skiils: Project Management, software developing, website designing, Consulting Capacity Building, Fundraising, Database designing, drafting policies, procedures, and guidelines, Strategic Planning & Change Management

ACCOMPLISHMENTS

Certifications

❖ A Workshop for Managers and Facilitators of Civic Education, Intermediary Development Consultants (IDC), United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF)

- ❖ Training on Decentralized Governance: Community Based Monitoring & Evaluation and Citizen Participation, United Nations System Staff College (UNSSC), United Nations Development Programme (UNDP)
- Training on Planning, Ministry of Planning and National Development, Somaliland

Honor & Award

Award title: Advocacy Reward Certificate

LANGUAGES

English: Professional working proficiency **Somali**: Native or bilingual proficiency

REFERENCE:

Name: MP. Ahmed Yaasiin Sheekh Cali Ayaanle Name: Mohamed Mohamoud Haashi

Title:ex-Vice-ChairmanTitle:ex-ChairmanInstitution:ParliamentInstitution:(SOLLA)

 Institution:
 Parliament
 Institution:
 (SOLLA)

 Telephone:
 +252-634456557
 Telephone:
 +252634197763/4129400

Name :Abdisamad Omar Maal Name: Deeqa Cabdi Yusuf
Title: Solicitor General Title: General Director of MOIP

Institution: Solicitor General Office Institution: Ministry of investment promotion

Email: maalcabdisamad@yahoo.com